Thiago R. Oliveira

Personal Summary

I am currently a Postdoctoral Researcher at the Centre for Social Investigation and a Research Fellow of Nuffield College in the University of Oxford. I am a criminologist who draws on theories from sociology, social policy, and psychology to investigate the implications of police (mis)conduct and policing policy to public recognition of legal authority and crime using methods from quantitative social science, econometrics, and data science.

- ♥ Centre for Social Investigation, Nuffield College, University of Oxford
- ★ ThiagoROliveira.com
- **y** @ROliveiraT
- Scholar

Professional Appointments

University of Surrey, Guildford, UK

· From Aug. 2022: Lecturer in Criminology, Department of Sociology

University of Oxford, Oxford, UK

- · Aug. 2021 present: Postdoctoral Researcher, Centre for Social Investigation, Nuffield College
- · Aug. 2021— present: Research Fellow, Nuffield College

EDUCATION

London School of Economics and Political Science, London, UK

Ph.D., Social Research Methods, 2017 - 2021

- Thesis: It's a matter of (change over) time: The role of police conduct on the dynamics of attitudes towards legal authority
- Supervisory team: Prof. Jonathan Jackson & Prof. Jouni Kuha
- Thesis examiners: Prof. Jeffrey Fagan & Dr. Amy Nivette

University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil

M.A., Sociology, 2014 - 2016

- Visiting Scholar, International Institute for the Sociology of Law (Oñati, Spain), Fall 2015
- Dissertation: Social mechanisms of judicial decisions: An explanatory mixed-methods research design on juvenile sentencing
 - * Award: Best M.A. dissertation concluded in the Department of Sociology in 2016

 $B.A.,\,\mathrm{Social}$ Sciences, 2010-2013

Professional Affiliations

- $\cdot\ 2022-present:\ Associate\ Member,\ Centre\ for\ Social\ Investigation,\ Nuffield\ College,\ University\ of\ Oxford$
- \cdot 2022—present: Associate, Department of Sociology, Harvard University
- · 2017—present: Associate Member, Centre for the Study of Violence, University of São Paulo

PREVIOUS PROFESSIONAL APPOINTMENTS

University College London, London, UK

- \cdot Sep. 2020 Jun. 2021: Associate Lecturer (Teaching) in Quantitative Research Methods and Data Analysis (QStep), Department of Political Science & School of Public Policy
- \cdot Sep. 2019 Feb. 2020: Teaching Fellow in Quantitative Research Methods, Department of Political Science & School of Public Policy

University of São Paulo, São Paulo, Brazil

· Apr. 2015— Aug. 2017: Researcher, Centre for the Study of Violence

Publications

Peer-Reviewed Papers

7. Oliveira, Thiago R. Conditionally accepted. "Aggressive policing and undermined legitimacy: Assessing the impact of police stops at gunpoint on perceptions of police in São Paulo, Brazil". Journal of Experimental Criminology. Preprint available at SocArXiv (https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/v58je/).

- Suss, Joel & Thiago R. Oliveira. Forthcoming. "Economic inequality and the spatial distribution of stop and search: Evidence from London". British Journal of Criminology.
- 5. Jackson, Jonathan, Krisztián Pósch, **Thiago R. Oliveira**, Ben Bradford, Silvia Camões, Ariadne Natal, & André Zanetic. 2022. "Fear and legitimacy in São Paulo, Brazil: police-citizen relations in a high violence, high fear city". *Law & Society Review*, 56(1): 122 145. (doi 10.1111/lasr.12589)
- 4. Oliveira, Thiago R. & Jonathan Jackson. 2021. "Legitimacy, trust and legal cynicism: A review of concepts". *Tempo Social*, 33(3): 113 145. (doi 10.11606/0103-2070.ts.2021.191381).
- 3. Oliveira, Thiago R., Jonathan Jackson, Kristina Murphy, & Ben Bradford. 2021. "Are trustworthiness and legitimacy 'hard to win, easy to lose'? A longitudinal test of the asymmetry thesis of police-citizen contact", *Journal of Quantitative Criminology*, 37:1003 1045. (doi 10.1007/s10940-020-09478-2)
- Jackson, Jonathan, Ian Bruton-Smith, Ben Bradford, Thiago R. Oliveira, Krisztián Pósch, & Patrick Sturgis. 2021. "Police legitimacy and the norm to cooperate: using a mixed effects location scale model to estimate the strength of social norms at a small spatial scale", *Journal of Quantitative Criminology*, 37: 547 – 572. (doi 10.1007/s10940-020-09467-5)
- Oliveira, Thiago R. 2019. "Juvenile Sentencing: A Mixed-Methods Approach", Brazilian Political Science Review, 13(1). (doi 10.1590/1981-3821201900010006)

Working Papers

- · Oliveira, Thiago R. "Violence and coercive policing: Dynamics and consequences of the overpolicing-underpolicing paradox in Brazil's largest city". Preprint available at SocArXiv (https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/89jkv).
 - Under review, Criminology.
- · Oliveira, Thiago R., Jonathan Jackson, Debora Piccirillo, Renan Theodoro de Oliveira, & Rick Trinkner. "Socialization through violence: Exposure to neighborhood and police violence and the developmental trajectories of legal legitimacy beliefs among adolescents in São Paulo". Preprint available at SocArXiv (https://osf.io/preprints/socarxiv/v3h97).
- · Oliveira, Thiago R., & David S. Kirk, "Does police use-of-force deter, or does it actually foster violent violent crime? Police misconduct and the cultural reproduction of legal cynicism in Chicago neighborhoods".
- · Oliveira, Thiago R., Marcos César Alvarez, & Bruna Gisi, "From an offender-based to an offense-based justice: Changes in sentencing patterns in the juvenile justice system in São Paulo from 1990 to 2006".

Asked to revise and resubmit, Crime, Law and Social Change.

Peer-Reviewed Papers in Portuguese

- 6. Theodoro, Renan, Debora Piccirillo, Aline Gomes, & Thiago R. Oliveira. 2022. 'Violência como fator socializador na construção da legitimidade da polícia: um estudo com adolescentes de São Paulo, Brasil'. Análise Social, Vol. VLII(2). (doi 10.31447/AS00032573.2022243.01). ['Violence as a socialising factor shaping police legitimacy: a study with adolescents in São Paulo, Brazil']
- 5. Oliveira, Thiago R., André Zanetic, & Ariadne Natal. 2020. "Preditores e impactos da legitimidade policial: testando a teoria da justeza procedimental em São Paulo", *Dados*, 63(1). (doi 10.1590/001152582020197).
 - ['Predictors and impacts of police legitimacy: testing the procedural justice theory in São Paulo']
- 4. Oliveira, Thiago R. André R. Oliveira, Sergio & Adorno, S. 2019. "Legitimidade policial: um modelo de mensuração", *Revista Brasileira de Ciências Sociais*, 34, 100. (doi 10.1590/3410007/2019).
 - ['Police legitimacy: a measurement model']
- 3. Oliveira, Thiago R. 2017. "Mecanismos sociais de decisões judiciais: um desenho misto explicativo sobre a aplicação da medida socioeducativa de internação", *Revista Brasileira de Sociologia*, 5(10), pp. 58-88. (doi 10.20336/rbs.205).

['Social mechanisms of judicial decisions: an explanatory mixed-methods research design on juvenile sentencing']

- Oliveira, Thiago R. 2017. "Oitivas cerimoniais: relatos descritivos do sistema de justiça juvenil em São Paulo", Confluências, 18(3), pp. 65-91. (doi 10.22409/confluências.v18i3.476).
 ['Ceremonial hearings: descriptive reports of the juvenile justice system in São Paulo']
- Zanetic, André, Bruno Paes Manso, Ariadne Natal, & Thiago R. Oliveira. 2016. "Legitimidade da polícia: segurança pública para além da dissuasão", Civitas Revista de Ciências Sociais, 16(4), pp. 148-173. (doi 10.15448/1984-7289.2016.4.24183).
 ['Police legitimacy: criminal policy beyond deterrence']

Selected Presentations

Guest lectures

- · "O que é e como promover legitimidade? Justiça procedimental e o papel da polícia na construção de crenças públicas na legitimidade das leis." *Curso NEV CAES 2022*, lecture to Brazilian police officers, June 2022.
 - ['What is and how to promote police legitimacy? Procedural justice and the role of the police in shaping public beliefs about the legitimacy of the law']
- "A legitimacy crisis among ethnic minorities? Understanding the 'defund the police' movement." Postgraduate module: Criminal Justice Systems, Department of Sociology, University of Surrey, March 2022.
- · "Police violence and police legitimacy: A legitimacy crisis among ethnic minorities?" Postgraduate module: *Police Violence and Racial Oppression*, Department of Sociology, University of Oxford, February 2022.
- · "Police-citizen contact and public attitudes towards legal authority: a longitudinal test of procedural justice policing." Postgraduate module: *Public Policy Analysis*, University of Minho, Portugal, May 2019.

Invited talks

- \cdot "Dynamics of the overpolicing-underpolicing paradox in São Paulo." Latin American Centre, University of Oxford, March 2022.
- · "Police use of force and legal cynicism: Preliminary findings from the Project on Human Development in Chicago Neighborhoods" (with David S. Kirk). London Policing Seminar Series, University College London, December 2021.
- · "Violence and coercive policing: Dynamics and consequences of the overpolicing-underpolicing paradox in Brazil's largest city." London Policing Seminar Series, University College London, October 2021.
- · "Violence and coercive policing: Dynamics and consequences of the overpolicing-underpolicing paradox in Brazil's largest city." Seminário NIED-CERES, UERJ/UFRJ, Brazil, September 2021.
- · "Social conservatism and legitimacy: predicting public support for police violence in São Paulo." Workshop *Trust in Justice*, University of Minho, Portugal, September 2017.
- · "Profiling mechanisms in the Brazilian juvenile justice system." Violence, media, and youth, SESC, Brazil, June 2017

Scientific meetings

· ASC · 2019, 2020 (cancelled), 2022 (planned)

· Eurocrim · 2017, 2019, 2022 (planned)

 $\begin{array}{ccc} \cdot \text{ ISA} & & \cdot \text{ 2018} \\ \cdot \text{ SBS (Brazil)} & & \cdot \text{ 2015, 2017} \end{array}$

· ANPOCS (Brazil) · 2013, 2014, 2015, 2016

Awards

LSE Class Teacher Award

2018/2019 - LSE Class Teacher Award nominated by the Department of Methodology

Departmental Award: Best Dissertation

2017 - Best M.A. dissertation concluded in 2016 in the Department of Sociology, University of São Paulo

Conference Award: Top 3 paper

2016 - VI Political Science Graduate Seminar, University of São Paulo

Grants and SCHOLARSHIPS Travel Fund

LSE Postgraduate Travel Fund, LSE - 2018, 2019: GBP 2,000.00

PhD scholarship

 $LSE\ PhD\ Studentship,\ LSE-2017-2021:\ GBP\ 140,000.00$

M.A. scholarship

Bolsa de mestrado, National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (CNPq) - 2014-2016:

BRL 36,000.00

Residence Grant

Residence Grant, International Institute for the Sociology of Law (IISL) - Nov-Dec 2015

Research Trainee (Research fellowship for undergraduate students)

Iniciação Científica, The São Paulo Research Foundation (FAPESP) - Jan-Dec 2013: BRL 7,000.00

Teaching EXPERIENCE 50th GESIS Spring Seminar

Causal Inference in Observational Studies

Co-lecturer: 2021 MSc/PhD level

University College London (UCL)

Introduction to Quantitative Methods (PUBL0055) Data Analysis (QStep) (POLS0010)

Class Teacher: 2019, 2020 Class Teacher: 2021

MSc level Undergraduate level (year 2)

London School of Economics and Political Science (LSE)

Intermediate Quantitative Methods (MY465)

Class Teacher (GTA): 2017, 2018 Instructor: 2019 MSc level

Mutivariate Analysis and Measurement (MY455)

Graduate Teaching Assistant: 2019

Msc/PhD level

Introduction to Quantitative Analysis (MY451)

Class Teacher (GTA): 2017

MSc level

Introduction to R Programming (MY591)

MSc/PhD level

Introduction to Quantitative Methods for Media

and Communications (MY464)

Co-Instructor: 2020

MSc level

University of São Paulo (USP)

Research Methods and Techniques (FSL0203) Prison in Modern Society (FSL0531) Teaching Assistant & Class leader: 2015, 2017 Undergraduate Teaching Assistant: 2013

Undergraduate level Undergraduate level

Reviewer Reviews in English

> Criminal Justice and Behavior, Criminology & Criminal Justice, Journal of Contemporary Criminal Justice, Latin American Research Review, Revista Salud Bosque, Victims & Offenders

Reviews in Portuguese

Dados: Revista de Ciências Sociais, Revista Brasileira de Ciências Sociais, Revista de Ciências Sociais,

Revista Eletrônica de Ciência Política, Revista Estudios Sociológicos, Tempo Social.

Professional SERVICES

Voluntary Consultant in Research and Data Analysis at StopWatch (2020-...)

Member of the Advisory Board, National Survey on Violence Against Children, Fundação José Luiz Egydio Setúbal (2021-...)

Coordinator of the LSE Quantitative Methods Reading Group (2020 – 2021)

PhD representative for the Teaching Committee, **Department of Methodology**, London School of Economics and Political Science (2018/2019)

Elected **Graduate Student Representative** in the **Department of Sociology**, University of São Paulo (2015)

Member of **Editorial Board** for **Primeiros Estudos** (journal organised by USP undergraduate students in Social Sciences) (2013 - 2014)

Computer Statistics

SKILLS R (proficient user and instructor), Mplus (proficient user), Stata (instructor), SPSS (instructor)

Miscellaneous

 $L\!\!\!/\!\!\!\!/ T_{\!E}\!X,\; \mathtt{RMarkdown},\; \mathtt{git}$

Languages English (fluent), Portuguese (native), Spanish (intermediate)

July 20, 2022